טוב *Tov*, alright. We are on the penultimate דף *daf* today. Today's
דף *daf* is... no, it's only 70 years. Today's דף *daf* is
צדי *Tzadi*. We pick up on the משנה mishna, *Mishna* on... where
are we?
Are we on the משנה Mishna. *Mishna*? No, we pick up in
the middle of דף *daf* צדי *Tzadi*, excuse me. We pick up
in the middle of דף *daf* צדי *Tzadi* where it says... okay...
לימא מסייע
ליה *Leima
Mesayei Lei*, right. So we are about let's see how many lines
down... 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11 lines
down, the middle line... לימא מסייע ליה *Leima Mesayei Lei*. And what
we've introduced was that in our משנה Mishna *Mishna* was a complicated
case about, you know, me being הנאה *hano'eh*... נהנה neheneh *neheneh* from
your father, me being הנאה *hano'eh* to you, but the bottom line
was, was that in addition to issues about עינוי נפש *inuy nefesh*
and so on... the משנה Mishna *Mishna* provided... the ברייתא braisa *braisa*
quoted the position of רבי דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*
that a case about a woman who said, you know, "I'm forbidden
to have sex with you if I have sex with you." So...
and רבי דוסא *Rabbi Dosa* said the husband cannot be מיפר meifer
*meifer*. And the question is like, "why not? It's all about עינוי
נפש *inuy nefesh* or דברים שבינו לבינה devarim shebeino leveinah, *devarim shebeino
leveina*." So basically the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*... assumed or asserted that רבי
דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*'s position was that the husband cannot be מיפר mefer
*meifer* of נדר neder *neder* until it actually has taken effect, עד
שיחול הנדר ad sheyachol haneder *ad sheyachol haneder*. And the חכמים Chachamim
*Chachamim* disagree. And then there was a fascinating story about somebody who
took a vow and he would... needed to go to a חכם
chacham *Chacham* to be מתיר matir *matir* it, and he was sort
of tricked into triggering the תנאי tenai *tnai* so that it would
be חל chal. *chal*, so then it would be הותר *hutar*, and
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said that that's because according to... who was
it? According to... רב אחא בר רב הונא *Rav Acha bar Rav
Huna*, who was the one who sort of tricked him and so
on... he felt that the same debate about הפרה hafara *hafara* applied
to התרה hatara, *hatara*. And therefore to satisfy the position of רבי
דוסא *Rabbi Dosa*, he wanted to make sure that the נדר neder.
*neder* had taken effect. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually put
out a position that is even more far-reaching, רב פפי *Rav Pappi*,
who says that when it... the whole debate was only by הפרה
hafara. *hafara*, but when it comes to התרה hatara *hatara*, everybody then...
there's no debate. Even the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* agree it has to
take effect. So that's interesting, right? Because if you would've asked us
intuitively, you could sort of see that הפרה hafara *hafara* is a,
you know, power that the husband has to sort of wipe it
away, and maybe that would require it actually exist for the נדר
neder *neder* and he overrules it... whereas התרה hatara *hatara* goes back
to the original act of taking the vow and... and it's through
this formal process, declares that original act to be in error, so
you would think that that could happen, you know, even... before the
vow has taken effect. So maybe... so why... you know, it's strange,
but this is the position of רב פפי *Rav Pappi*, that when
it comes to התרה hatara, *hatara*, everybody agrees it has to take
effect. So not exactly clear why. He gets it from a פסוק
*pasuk*, לא יחל lo yachel, דברו devaro, *Lo yachel devaro*... so the
word יחל *yachel*... חל *chal*, take effect, so it can only be
un-חל *chal* after it's been חל *chal*. It can only be voided
after it's been חל *chal*, and that's the פסוק *pasuk* from which
we learn that a חכם hakham *Chacham* can be מתיר הנדר *matir
haneder*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up with the following:
לימא מסייע ליה *Leima Mesayei Lei*. Let's come and support... see if
we can support the position of רב פפי *Rav Pappi* that everybody
agrees התרה hatara *hatara* only works after it's been taken... after it's
taken effect. קונם konam שאיני נהנה neheneh לפלוני *Konam she'eini ne'eneh liploni*...
a person says a קונם *Konam* that I will not be נהנה
*neheneh*... the lamed here is always a... question, right? Is it מפלוני
*mi-Ploni* or לפלוני *li-Ploni*? The רן Ran. *Ran* here assumes it means
literally לפלוני *li-Ploni*, although a lot of times it means מפלוני *mi-Ploni*.
Anyway, I... פלוני *Ploni* won't get any benefit from me is how
the רן Ran *Ran* reads it, but I think you could just
as easily read it... funny, we're at the end... we're at the
end of מסכת Massekhet. נדרים nedarim *Maseches Nedarim* and we still don't
know which way to read these... ו *vovs*? ב *bets*? Because the
grammar... it's all sort of vernacular, so it's always funny. I know.
I know. So that's a problem. Anyway, either I won't get benefit
from פלוני *Ploni* or he won't get benefit from me, anyway... let's
do it the רן Ran *Ran*'s way, why not? So I won't
get benefit from... פלוני *Ploni* won't get benefit from me ולמי שנשאל
לו עליו *u-lemishanishal lo alav* and if I ever go to a
חכם *Chacham* to be מתיר *matir* this נדר neder *neder*, then I'm
also אסור Assur *assur*... then that חכם *Chacham* also can't get any
benefit from me. Okay. So two people he made אסור *assur*. Okay,
or he אסור *assur*'d himself to, but anyway, we're going by the
רן Ran *Ran*. You know, the... פלוני *Ploni*, ראובן *Reuven*, and the
חכם *Chacham* who will undo the נדר neder, *neder* if it should
ever be undone. So it's like a Moebius נדר neder.
*neder*.
Exactly. Okay. So then the... so then the... the ברייתא braisa. *braisa*
says... נשאל על הראשון ואחר כך נשאל על השני Nishal al harishon
ve'achar kach nishal al hasheini. *nishal al harishon ve'achar kach nishal al
hasheini*, get התרה hatara *hatara* for the first one and then get
התרה hatara. *hatara* for the second one. So you get התרה hatara
*hatara* for the first one, for ראובן *Reuven*, and you got it
from... from... חכם *Chacham* Cohen here, and then after חכם *Chacham* Cohen
gave you... then he became אסור *assur*, so then you went to
another חכם *Chacham* and you got it undone for חכם *Chacham* Cohen.
Okay. So get... do the first one, have the איסור *issur* then
חל *chal* for the חכם *Chacham*, and then go and then undo
the איסור *issur* that was... Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
ואי אמרת נשאל אף על פי שלא חל הנדר *ve-ee amarta nish'al
af al pi shelo chal haneder* if you say you could be
מתיר *matir* a נדר neder, *neder* before take effect, איבעי אהאי נשאל
ברישא ואיבעי אהאי נשאל ברישא *ibaye ahay nish'al be-reisha ve-ibaye ahay nish'al
be-reisha*. Why? What difference does it make what order you do? Go
ahead and get get undone the חכם *Hacham* one first. It doesn't
need to have yet taken effect. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers
ומי ידע אי האי קמאי אי האי בתראי *umi yada ee hay
kamay ee hay batray*? How do you know how to read this
ברייתא *Braita*? The ברייתא *Braita* says be נשאל *nish'al* on the first
one and then נשאל *nish'al* on the second. The first doesn't have
to mean the first one you took. It just means be נשאל
*nish'al* on one and then be נשאל *nish'al* on the other. Now
that is a very bad read of the ברייתא *Braita*. First of
all, if that's all the ברייתא *Braita* is telling me, who needs
a ברייתא *Braita* to tell me that? You took a נדר neder,
*neder* whatever, be נשאל *nish'al* on one then be נשאל *nish'al* on
the other. And anyway why can't I just be נשאל *nish'al* on
both at the same time? Because if I'm on both at the
same time the same חכם *Hacham* that is מתיר *matir*-ing the נדר
neder, *neder* is the one that's אסור *assur* and you can't sort
of be like a נוגע בדבר *nogaya b'davar* if you're a party
to the נדר *neder*. Right? So you understand why you can't do
both at the same time? Because if I'm מתיר *matir* your נדר
*neder* for ראובן *Reuven* and for the חכם *Hacham* who's מתיר *matir*
then I'm מתיר *matir* your נדר *neder* for ראובן *Reuven* and for
me. So you need to separate it. One חכם *Hacham* is מתיר
*matir* for ראובן *Reuven* and a different חכם *Hacham* is מתיר *matir*
for that חכם *Hacham*. So they have to be
sequential. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying רישא *reisha* does not
necessarily mean the first one you took. It means first do it
on one and then do it on the other one and that's
all the ברייתא *Braita* is teaching. Now I want to point out
that there was another interesting approach that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* could
have taken which it didn't and I actually maybe because I was
so much thought this was the answer that I read that into
the words of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* which was until I saw
that the ר"ן Ran *Ran* and everybody else read it differently which
was there's a יש ברירה *yesh breira* type of a problem here.
Meaning if I were to try... the problem is not just that
the נדר *neder* hasn't been חל *chal* for the חכם *Hacham* yet.
The problem is we don't know who that חכם *Hacham* is, right?
And I can say I'm intending to go over there to Rabbi
Cohen, we'll make it Rabbi now so
sorry for the ספרדים *Sefardim*
out there, I'm intending to go to Rabbi Cohen over there and
I go to and I go to a different Rabbi and I
say once I get this נדר *neder* הותר *hutar* by Rabbi Cohen
he's going to be אסור *assur* could you מתיר *matir* me to
Rabbi Cohen? But the problem is there's nothing to determine that it
is going to be Rabbi Cohen. You might change your mind and
that Rabbi that's going to be אסור *assur* could be a different
Rabbi. So how could you be מתיר *matir* a נדר *neder* when
the person who it affects, right, is not yet determined? So I
don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not say that. To
me that's like the obvious answer. It doesn't have to be חל
*chal* but you can't be מתיר *matir* a נדר *neder* if you
don't know its parameters. Okay anyway so for whatever reason the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say that and it just rereads this ברייתא *Braita*
to say first might not really mean first. Yes Michael.
So if I make a נדר *neder* I won't have any benefit
from any חכמים Chachamim *Hachamim* there's no way of getting out of
it then, right?
Well you get three laypeople.
Okay fine but if I say...
possibly I don't know, it's a good question. Maybe not. Alright so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אלא לימא מסייע ליה *Ella leima
mesaya
lay*.
Let's try to support you from another ברייתא *Braita*. קונם שאיני נהנה
לפלוני הריני נזיר nazir. לכשאשאל עליו *Konam she-ayni nehena le-Ploni hareni nazir
le-kshe-esha'el alav*. So קונם *Konam* I won't get any benefit from, we'll
read it my way now, from ראובן *Reuven* and if I ever
get this נדר *neder* undone I'll be a נזיר *Nazir*. Alright so
that's less complicated than you know the חכם *Hacham* who undoes it
I'll be אסור *assur*. I'll be a נזיר *Nazir* if I ever
get this נדר *neder* undone. נשאל על נדרו ואחר כך נשאל על
נזרו *Nish'al al nidro ve-achar kach nish'al al nizro*. So go ahead
and get נדר *neder* one undone
and then get your נזירות nezirus *Nezirut* undone. So you can't say
which is ראשון *rishon* which is שני *sheni*. It's very clear נדר
*neder* and נזירות nezirus *Nezirut*. So why do you have to do
it in that order?
Why don't you just do them both at the same time or
the נזירות nezirus *Nezirut* first? Wait a minute let's finish. ואי אמרת
נשאל אף על פי שלא חל הנדר *ve-ee amarta nish'al af al
pi shelo chal haneder* if you say you could be נשאל *nish'al*
without it take effect yet איבעי על נדרו איבעי על נזרו איבעי
ברישא *ibaye al nidro ibaye al nizro ibaye be-reisha*. Go get your
נזירות nezirus *Nezirut* undone. You say I made this vow that would
be triggered when a certain תנאי *tnay*... I made נזירות *Nezirut* that
would be triggered when a certain condition is met
and I regret having made it and I don't want it to
be חל *chal* when that condition is met and get it undone.
Who needs to first get the נדר *neder* the first נדר *neder*
undone? So that's a very good proof that this ברייתא *Braita* assumes
you have to have the נדר *neder* take effect. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson. היא *Rabbi Natan hi*. You
know what? You're right. Fine. The ברייתא *Braita* proves the נדר *neder*
had to take effect but it doesn't substantiate your claim that it's
דברי הכל *divrei hakol*, right? Maybe it's רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson, *Rabbi
Natan*. Now of course it's taught anonymously so it does sound more
consensus. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine that very clearly
proves it has to take effect before you do התרה hatara *hatara*
but it might be limited to רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson, *Rabbi Natan*.
Yes Michael what do you want? I'm sure we'll get more into
this in נזיר *Nazir* but in נזיר *Nazir* isn't there like an
עניין *inyan* of הפלאה hafla'ah *hafla'ah*?
Is considered a good הפלאה *hafla'ah*? Because it seems so vague you
don't even know if it's ever going to...
Oh, that's if it's, yeah, you are right that it has to
be sort of like, there is a position like that that נזירות
cannot be בתנאי, betnai, but we don't rule that way. There is
other ways in which נזירות has to be like not have indeterminate
aspects to it, but here once the נזירות is triggered, then the
נזירות is determined. But it's a very good point, you are correct.
There are some positions like that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, so what we have said
is a claim that either the same debate about הפלאה by, about
הפרה hafara by התרה, hatara or everybody agrees by התרה hatara it
has to take effect, and we have a ברייתא that seems to
say by התרה hatara? it has to take effect, but maybe that's
limited to רבי נתן. Rabbi Nosson Now we get a third possibility.
אמר רבינא אמר ליה ממרימר, Amar Ravina amar lei Mareimar,
ממרימר Mareimar said to רבינא, Ravina, הכי אמר אבוך משמיה דרב, Hachi
amar avuch mishmei deRav, משמיה דרב פפי, mishmei deRav Pappi, excuse me,
in the name of Rav Pappi. So it's the same Rav Pappi
but it's a different version of Rav Pappi. מחלוקת בהפרה. Machlokes behafara.
The debate is by הפרה. hafara אבל בשאלה, Aval beshe'eila, when it
comes to
התרה, hatara דברי הכל מפר ואף על פי שלא חל הנדר. divrei
hakol meifer ve'af al pi shelo chal haneder. Everybody agrees it could
be done without it taking effect. So clearly Rav Pappi said when
it comes to התרה hatara everybody agrees. The question is everybody agrees
which way? So until now we've been assuming everybody agrees that it
needs to take effect, here's a version of Rav Pappi that everybody
agrees it does not need to take effect. And as we pointed
out there's something very intuitive about that because since it's about establishing
a sense of טעות, ta'os, who needs for it to have taken
effect? Anyway let's see why and let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with it. דכתיב לא יחל דברו. Dechsiv lo yachel devaro. So
before we emphasized לא יחל, it has to be חל. Now we're
emphasizing דברו, as soon as you speak it even if it hasn't
taken effect you can go ahead and void the speech act.
No, others can.
Others can, right, you can't, others can, thank you. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to go through the same issue. So
the גמרא Gemara says למימרא דלא הוי דברו Lemeimra delo havei devaro
even before it becomes effective. So the גמרא Gemara says מיתיבי, Meiseivi,
I ask you on this: קונם שאיני נהנה לפלוני ולמי שנשאל עליו.
Konam she'eini neheneh lepeloni ulemi shenishal alav. So this case, I won't
be נהנה from Reuven and I won't then be נהנה from the
חכם who I get a התר heter from. נשאל על הראשון ואחר
כך נשאל על השני. You first do one and then the other.
So why do you have, again we're assuming like we initially assumed
that it means דוקא davka in that order. ואמאי, Ve'amai, so according
to you why do you have to do it in that order?
אי בעי האי נשאל ברישא ואי בעי האי נשאל ברישא. Ei ba'ei
hai nishal bereisha ve'ei ba'ei hai nishal bereisha. You said that when
it comes to התרה hatara you can get it undone before it
takes effect, so get the second one done first, why not? So
the גמרא Gemara says מי יודע היי ראשון והיי שני? Mi yodeia
hai rishon vehai sheini? How do you know which what's meant by
first and second? Just means one and then the other, it doesn't
mean the first one you took. You can't prove anything from that.
Okay, but we can prove something from the next ברייתא. מיתיבי. Meiseivi.
קונם שאיני נהנה והריני נזיר לכשנשאל עליו. Konam she'eini neheneh vehareini nazir
lecheshenishal alav. A קונם I won't get benefit and and if I
get that undone I'll become a נזיר. נשאל על נדרו ואחר כך
נשאל על נזירותו. Nishal al nidro ve'achar kach nishal al neziroso. First
get your נדר undone and then get your נזירות undone. Why does
it have to be that order? This shows that at least according
to one opinion, at least according to רבי נתן, Nason, it has
to take effect. So the גמרא Gemara says alright
so it's not so clearly somebody says it has to take effect
first by a התרה. hatara ואמאי, Ve'amai, why is that true? אי
בעי על נדרו נשאל ברישא ואי בעי על נזירותו נשאל ברישא. Ei
ba'ei al nidro nishal bereisha ve'ei ba'ei al neziroso nishal bereisha. According
to you you should be able to undo either one first. So
the גמרא says תיובתא, Tiyufta, alright you're right, goodbye that opinion. Okay,
so clearly there is an opinion out there that by התרה hatara
you need it to be take effect, and according to one opinion
earlier everybody said by התרה Hatara you needed it to take effect.
So how do we פסקן pasken about all this? Well, as you
Michael, I asked your question for you, I know, because we have
a little extra time and there's an interesting ר"ן. Ran So anyway
so by by הפרה hafara it's clear, it's a debate of the
חכמים and רבי נתן, Nason and therefore by הפרה hafara you can
get undone even before it took effect. The ר"ן Ran actually points
that out and this is why I thought it was interesting because
it was a question we raised. The ר"ן actually points out that
that's already implicit from the סוגיא sugya before. If you remember the
סוגיא sugya before was a woman who took a vow when she
wasn't, when she was married and then it took effect thirty days
later when she was divorced or vice versa and רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva basically says you are, the husband is מיפר mefer, the vow
when it was taken and based on the status when it was
taken. So clearly you see when it comes to הפרה hafara we
rule like the חכמים that it could be undone before it was
that it could that you could have the הפרה hafara before it
takes effect. Now interestingly there are two there are two
potential problems with this.
No, before we even get to התרה Hatara which is much more
interesting for us but there are two potential challenges to this. Number
one is in the story about the guy
that whatever the guy that made a vow on a תנאי and
he was tricked into making it take effect etc. so there the
גמרא sort of said well he wanted to make it he wanted
to make it take effect because he thinks הפרה hafara. because the
rabbi thought that התרה hatara is the same as הפרה hafara and
he wanted to be יוצא yotzei the position of רבי נתן Nason.
that says it has to take effect. So the... So the fact
that in that story there's an attempt to try to be יוצא
yotzei the position of Rabbi
נתן, Nason some ראשונים rishonim say, well maybe that means we פסקן
pasken by Rabbi נתן Nason even by הפרה hafara, because he cares
about the position of Rabbi נתן. Nason
So anyway, that's all the evidence in all the גמרות Gemoras as
the ר"ן points out is not that way. And but nevertheless some
want to say, well, I don't know, maybe Rabbi נתן even by
הפרה. hafara? Number one. Number two is what do you do with
the earlier debate though if you say by Rabbi נתן by הפרה
hafara it has to take effect, what about that earlier debate with
Rabbi עקיבא Akiva that it could be thirty days later and you
could do it now? So here and this makes a lot of
sense and it's a point that we did not make, that even
when Rabbi נתן says it has to take effect if it's conditional,
that's only if the condition is like it's questionable if and when
it'll ever be triggered. If I just postpone the effect, I basically
it's definitely taken effect, it's just taken effect thirty days later, right?
So that's not conditional. That was the debate of Rabbi עקיבא Akiva
if you remember before and when Rabbi עקיבא Akiva said if the
woman says in thirty days, the husband, you know, annuls the vow
now. So that might be an issue that nobody debates because that
is not really conditional, it's a postponing of the effect, but it's
not really conditional. When it's conditional and you don't know if the
condition will be triggered, it's not so clear that we can know
that that we should derive anything from the earlier position of Rabbi
עקיבא. Akiva. Okay, so A, that's interesting at least for me to
distinguish between an idea of postponing the effect and a conditional, that
the point here although we said עד שיחול הנדר which seems to
emphasize it has to take effect, right, it's maybe a different way
of learning it as it can't be conditional while I annul it.
If it's not conditional maybe I could do it even before it's
taken effect. So that's just for me an interesting like you know
intellectual distinction between those two ideas. Anyway, bottom line though over clearly
the overwhelming consensus of the ראשונים, rishonim, the overwhelming evidence in the
גמרא is that we פסקן pasken like the חכמים when it comes
to הפרה, Hafara it can be annulled before it takes effect. But
how about התרה? hatarah Because when it comes to התרה there's a
position of רב פפא Rav Pappa that says that everybody agrees that
it has to take effect first, right? So that would really seem
like and this is relevant I mean again I don't know how
many people take vows nowadays, I told you I've had to do
התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. How many people take vows on conditions is
you know I'm sure it happens also. Okay and according to this,
right, person took a vow on a condition, they regret it a
minute afterwards, you'd have to wait till it took effect. Okay, so
that actually seems to be the פסק. psak. So if you take
a look at the ר"ן on the top of צ"ב עמוד ב'
Tzadi-Beis amud beis where we are, he says the following: ולענין שאלה
קיימא לן כרב פפא דלא מחלוקת בהפרה אבל בשאלה דברי הכל אין
חכם מתיר עד שיחול הנדר. U'le'inyan she'ela kaima lan k'Rav Pappa d'la
machlokes b'hafara aval b'she'ela divrei hakol ein chacham matir ad sheyachol haneder.
Okay,
so it has to take effect. Everybody would say that like רב
פפא. Rav Pappa. Okay. והכי פסקו רבוותא זכרונם לברכה כוותיה לחומרא V'hachi
pasku rabu'asa zichronam livracha k'voseih l'chumra
and that's how like the great rabbis have פסקן'ד pasken'd like him
you know to be strict although there is the other position that
it's the same debate. ואיכא מן דאמר דאפילו הכי האומר קונם עלי
דבר פלוני לאחר שלשים יום V'ika man d'amar d'afilu hachi ha'omer konam
alai davar ploni l'achar shloshim yom and here's where that theoretical distinction
we mentioned a minute ago could be relevant even for us because
if we פסקן pasken for התרה it has to take effect. What
if it hasn't taken effect but it's not conditional? It's just delayed.
What would be that דין? din? Same question that we asked a
minute ago. חל הנדר מקרי וחכם מתיר דלא פליגי רבי נתן ורבנן
אלא בתולה נדרו בדבר שאפשר שלא יחול הנדר לעולם Chal haneder mikrei
v'chacham matir d'lo pligi Rabbi Nason v'Rabbanan ela b'solei nidro b'davar she'efshar
she'lo yachol haneder l'olam
that it really is conditional and might never take effect. אבל תולה
נדרו בימים Aval toleh nidro b'yamim when you basically say after a
passage of days, כיון שסוף איסורו לבוא keivan she'sof issuro lavo eventually
it will take effect. Okay, so it's really not conditional, it's really
postponed. אף על פי שלא חל עדיין חכם מתיר Af al pi
she'lo chal adayin chacham matir so some say that you can do
it in that case. ואיכא מן דאמר V'ika man d'amar some say
no, אפילו בכי האי גוונא כיון שמכל מקום עדיין אינו נאסר אין
חכם מתיר. afilu b'chai hai gavna keivan she'mikol makom adayin eino ne'esar
ein chacham matir. וסברא קמא טריצא טפי V'sevara kama tritza tfei he
says
I actually do like the first opinion better, there's a big difference
between being conditional and being postponed. So the question becomes we פסקן
pasken like רב פפא Rav Pappa by התרה and then the question
becomes how do we understand it? Are we saying that you cannot
annul a vow while it's conditional because and then you can understand
that? If it's still conditional maybe there's no vow for me to
annul, maybe there never will be a vow, how can I relate
to it as a vow if it if it might never take
effect, right? So that's a way of saying you can't do it
if it's a conditional. The other way is saying no you can't
do it like the more literally what the גמרא says until it
actually has taken effect. So and the נפקא מינה nafka mina between
those two is when you postpone it. It definitely will happen, there's
definitely a vow waiting to take effect, it definitely will take effect,
it just hasn't yet, okay? And that's the debate whether we can
do it at that stage. But in
general the general פסק psak is like רב פפא Rav Pappa that
by התרה we wait for it to take effect. All right, now
we get to the very last משנה, Mishnah yes.
Does this also just in your opinion don't you think that also
underscores the conceptual difference between התרה and הפרה? Hafara Right? In other
words, something's got to take effect in order for you then untie
it so to speak
whereas הפרה hafara is like an erasure like a like
a...
erasing even the intent.
Yeah, but the problem is that it's not that way, right? הפרה
hafara works, that's what I'm saying, התרה works by retroactively saying it
was a mistake. Look, just think about this difference. When התרה works,
it says that there was never a נדר. When הפרה works, it
just says from this point on, it's no longer effective, right? So
that's what we say, הפרה is מכאן ולהבא. mika'an u'le'haba. If a
woman transgressed her נדר and the בעל ba'al and the husband was
מיפר mefer. it after she transgressed, she still transgressed. But if you
transgressed your נדר and a חכם is מתיר it, you haven't transgressed.
So right, that's all the more would that seem to say that
by הפרה it has to be about the vow being in effect
and stopping its effect, whereas by התרה it's about the taking, the
act of taking. So to me it's still counterintuitive that the you
know I like רב פפא's Rav Pappa second opinion even though it
was rejected by the גמרא for good reason, yes.
If we say that for a father that he has to wait
till it takes effect, right? You said like 30 days from now,
but יום שמעו, yom shamo'o, I heard it now but it takes
effect 30 days later.
Yeah, so that goes to what we said before, that יום שמעו
yom shamo'o could be defined by a meaningful hearing. So the same
way it could be affected by if you realize that you're in
the position to be מיפר, it certainly could be effective, it could
be conditional on when you actually have the power to be מיפר.
He has to have like a calendar reminder then.
Exactly. That's all the more reason why we need our like iPhones.
Okay. So, we now come to the last משנה. Mishnah, Now I
have to tell you that this last משנה Mishnah in terms of
its הלכה halakha implications is probably more far reaching you know and
applies to more areas of הלכה halakha than probably the entire מסכת.
Massekhet Maybe that's an overstatement but I don't think so. Okay. I
mean the entire מסכת Massekhet? is very meaningful if somebody takes a
נדר, but that's limited to that little you know it's I mean
like I said it's not like these questions so happen, but okay,
we try to avoid them and they happen you know in very
small narrow occasions. Let's take a look at this משנה mishna which
only indirectly touches on issues of נדרים but has profound, profound human
application. Okay, so let's take a look. Yes, I know, well maybe.
בראשונה היו אומרים, barishona hayu omrim, they used to say, שלש נשים
יוצאות ונוטלות כתובה. shalosh nashim yotz'ot ve-notlot ketubba. Three women get divorced
and get their כתובה. ketubba. Okay, not just three women, but it
means women that come with the following claims even if they're somewhat
unsubstantiated or we'll take a look. Now they get, we force the
husband to divorce them and B we say it's not their fault
and therefore they're entitled to a כתובה. ketubba.
Why is this in this מסכת?
Well you will see, because one of them has to do with
a נדר. Okay. האומרת טמאה אני לך. ha-omeret teme'a ani lakh. Number
one, a woman who says I am tamei to you which basically
means either I was violated which would be relevant for a כהן
kohen because even if a woman is raped, she's forbidden to her
husband, or it means I committed adultery. Okay, so this happens, right?
But if I commit adultery why is she getting כתובה?
ketubba? So that is a good question and we will, the גמרא
is going to say therefore it has to be the case of
כהן. kohen. Okay, but this happens. It happens that a
wife of a כהן kohen is raped. It happens that it happens
that a woman commits adultery. It happens that a woman you know
has sex before she's married in a way that would make her
forbidden to her husband who's a כהן kohen and she goes ahead
and she tells her husband or I'll get later to the question
her husband to be. Okay, and the first approach was we believe
her. She said it, we believe her. So she said that she's
forbidden to him and he's forbidden to her. We can't let the
marriage continue that way. Okay, and there's a principle of שויא נפשה
חתיכה דאיסורא. shavya nafsheh chatikha de'issura. She basically has been defining has
made a declaration that she is forbidden to him. Now he could
say I don't believe you and you know so but but if
he does believe her then he also makes her to him a
חתיכה דאיסורא chatikha de'issura and who knows what the original reason was?
Maybe it wasn't even based on שויא, shavya, maybe it was based
on an assumption that women would not lie about such
things. What about אתקינו דיבורא atkino dibura or whatever? That's not really
relevant. Anyway, we're not nobody's executing her. Okay. So maybe it's based
on assumption maybe it's based on שויא, shavya, maybe it's based on
an assumption that people wouldn't lie about such a thing and therefore
we are going ahead and act on that and force a divorce.
Now why does she get כתובה? ketubba? That doesn't make sense if
she committed adultery. So therefore the גמרא is going to say that
we're assuming the כתובה ketubba part assumes that she was the אשת
כהן eishes kohen who's raped. Okay. And therefore she wasn't to blame,
she gets the כתובה. ketubba. But the believing her presumably would be
initially and then we'll talk about the second stage as well when
they reverse this ruling, would be with or without the כתובה. ketubba.
Okay. The כתובה ketubba is a case when it wasn't her fault.
Okay. But that's so that was the case of an אשת כהן
eishes kohen who's raped. But either but regardless it seems a woman
says this is my story, okay, we believe you. Can't let the
marriage continue.
That's a way to get out
of marriage she doesn't like. So that's going to be the second
stage. Okay. So that was stage number one. Stage number two, שמים
ביני לבינך. shamayim beini le-veinecha.
God is between us, heaven is between us. Now what does this
mean? So the גמרא is going to understand that it basically means
that the woman... God is my witness that this marriage can't continue,
and meaning nobody else knows and nobody else presumably is in a
position to know, which means that it has to do with some
aspect of their intimate life, so the גמרא's going to assume that
basically it means that she says you are not able to be
the phrase the גמרא uses is יורה כחץ Yoreh Kechetz which fertile
but more specifically right let's just be say what the גמרא says
which is יורה כחץ Yoreh Kechetz which means like shoot like an
arrow okay in terms of semen and ejaculation and so on and
therefore I can't get pregnant with you and and therefore I demand
a divorce. Now interestingly because the גמרא in כתובות Ketubot deals with
the fact that a woman is
not commanded on פרו ורבו. Pru Urvu. So okay what do you
mean you want a divorce who says you're entitled to kids you're
not being prevented from doing a מצוה. Mitzvah. Nevertheless the גמרא says
that a woman is also can say טעמא דמצוה Ta'ama d'Mitzvah as
a human being right I want to have kids and so on
and I want as a way the גמרא frames it is who's
going to take care of me in my old age and that's
a legitimate claim. So you can't give me kids I demand a
divorce. All right interestingly I will say parenthetically it doesn't say that
the claim could be you're not able to fulfill the מצוה Mitzvah
of עונה Onah right of marital sex because they could have sex
it's just an issue about you know ejaculation and whatever and and
being able to have kids but so apparently that problem is not
enough of a problem to say that it's not fulfilling the מצוה
Mitzvah of עונה. Onah. Okay that's interesting parenthesis. Anyway so she says
so if that were true she'd be entitled to a divorce it's
not her fault it's his fault based on what she's claiming okay
and it says we would believe her and we'd believe her in
two ways. Number one is we'd force a divorce and number two
is we'd believe her to say that the כתובה Ketubah has to
get paid. Right you could have said we could have made a
split decision in all these cases. Believe them enough to get a
divorce don't believe them enough to say that that they get paid
for you know that there's assumed as especially so anyway so that
was no but we believed her across the board okay presumably based
on I don't know it wouldn't be based on you know what
do you call it פה שבייה Peh Shvuyah this so the פה
שבייה שנשבית Peh Shvuyah shenishbet sure can't be relevant here it's just
based on we don't assume that people would lie about such a
thing. Okay that's number one. Number two. Number three is now by
the way it does yeah it doesn't make obviously it doesn't make
a difference right. Now number two oh by the way I should
say the phrase שמים ביני לבינך Shamayim beini l'veinecha
so as I said the simple way is just God knows only
God can testify okay but the ר"ן has an interesting
suggestion that maybe it's not enough to say that you can't give
me kids she also has to say say like and you know
and that's destroying our marriage and if you and that שמים Shamayim
he quotes ירושלמי Yerushalmi and שמים ביני לבינך Shamayim beini l'veinecha might
be a way of saying that we're far from one another as
heaven and earth. Okay so it's actually a claim about marital incompatibility.
So let's read that in the ר"ן because that's interesting. Now not
to so if you take a look like this he says ואף
על גב דאמרינן באגדה Ve'af al gav d'amrinan b'Agadah it is a
sixth line down before the lines get wide ואף על גב דאמרינן
באגדה Ve'af al gav d'amrinan b'Agadah שאמרה לו שרה אמנו לאברהם השמים
ביני לבינך She'amrah lo Sarah Immeinu l'Avraham Hashamayim beini l'veinecha סבירא ליה
יפרוט השם ביני ובינך Sevirah lei yiphrot Hashem beini uveinecha okay so
so now the question is so I didn't see this in my
הגדה Haggadah on פסח Pesach so then he gets is what he
means המדרש? HaMidrash?
Yeah אגדה Agadah and the difference between אגדה Agadah and הגדה Haggadah
it was you know not always you know it's I think where
it was not consistent. You often אגדתא Agadata was considered הגדה. Haggadah.
Okay so anyway okay so it's an אגדה Agadah that says that
שרה Sarah says to אברהם השמים ביני לבינך Abraham Hashamayim beini l'veinecha
סבירא ליה יפרוט השם ביני ובינך. Sevirah lei yiphrot Hashem beini uveinecha.
Okay so
now the question is so היינו שהוא מרוחק ממנו לגמרי Hainu shehu
meruchak mimenu legamre wait wait I want to try I want to
try to remember what question he's answering one minute היינו שהוא מרוחק
ממנו לגמרי
כגון שרה שהיתה תרעומת על אברהם שריחקה מחמת הגר. Hainu shehu meruchak
mimenu
legamre kegon Sarah shehaytah
taromet al Avraham sherichakah machmat Hagar.
Yeah
I'm trying to remember why he says that it has to do
with the ריחוק richuk one minute because then
he'd have to divorce her.
Yeah but why isn't it just
enough to say I want a kid?
One minute.
I
am not sure what's bothering him about this made sense when I
read it last night. Anyway let's keep on reading a little bit
maybe it'll come clear to me. Anyway okay שריחקה מחמת הגר. sherichakah
machmat Hagar. ובירושלמי נמי הכי משמע דאמרינן כמא דשמים רחוקה מן ארעא
U'v'Yerushalmi nami hachi mashma d'amrinan k'ma d'Shamayim rechukah min ar'a the same
way the heaven is as distance from the earth כך היא איתתא
רחיקה מבעלה. kach hi iteta rechika m'ba'alah. Okay
now by the way that's interesting because ירושלמי Yerushalmi this is really
the point I'm not getting exactly the question about שרה Sarah and
אברהם Avraham but this really is the relevant point the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
seems to read השמים ביני לבינך Hashamayim beini l'veinecha that she doesn't
even have to claim that you're not able to give me kids.
It's enough to claim that there is just a marital discord between
us and we are completely estranged from one another and the husband
is claiming it's not true and we would still believe the wife.
According to the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi*, אפשר דלשון השמים ביני לבינך כולל
הכל *efshar d'lashon Hashamayim beini l'beinecha kolel hakol*. So he is trying
to say, well, maybe השמים ביני לבינך *Hashamayim beini l'beinecha* includes both
ideas: we're emotionally distant or we're estranged and this problem. אבל הכא
מוכח בגמרא שפירשו שאינו יורה כחץ yoreh kachetz. *Aval hacha muchach b'Gemara
she'pirshu she'eino yoreh k'chetz*. דהכי קאמר השמים ביני לבינך הכי קאמר אלהים
עד ביני ובינך דקושטא קאמינא שדבר זה אינו ידוע בו אלא לשם
*D'hachi ka'amar Hashamayim beini l'beinecha hachi ka'amar Elokim eid beini uveinecha d'kushta
kamina shedavar zeh eino yadua bo ela laShem*. Okay, but what is
interesting is the possibility that this means for the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi*
maybe only the idea of estrangement and that she would be believed
just on that claim, okay, or combining the two, we're, you know,
this is this problem and we're estranged from one another and so
on. Okay, so and so
that's interesting because, you know, it gets to this issue if a
woman is suing for divorce, right? Here just the question about proving
it, right? But let's say nowadays, I don't know, something like this
could be proved. Go to a doctor's office, let's get it tested,
let's get it proved or whatever. So it's still relevant whether we
believe the woman or not to say what is a substantial enough
claim for divorce. And to say like the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* that estrangement,
right, for פשט *pshat* obviously that makes a lot of sense, but
for the גמרא *Gemara* it's not necessarily taken for granted it's substantial
enough, you know, and then it just becomes a question of do
we believe her or not, that is a big חידוש *chiddush*. And
I should say by the way that רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*, I think
I might have mentioned this before in another context,
basically bridges the gap if you would, right, and sort of is
able to make every case of estrangement a case about sex. And
he basically says that the woman says, I'm so estranged from him,
I find it intolerable to have sex with him, okay, and then
therefore that becomes it's not necessarily the issue of פרו ורבו *pru
u'rvu* and I need to have kids or so on, but then
for the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* that becomes the legitimate claim. רמב"ם Rambam,
*Rambam* says we will not force a person to be in a
marriage without sex or to have sex with a person that they
can't tolerate. Okay, so therefore it sort of makes it just ups
the stakes of the estrangement and sort of brings in this other
factor. So this is a really important question. There's one question about
who do we believe and there's another question like, you know, is
that fundamentally a legitimate claim, right? Okay, yeah, let's start with David,
yes.
So, didn't we have a comment the other day that a woman
is not in these days of the משנה mishna *Mishnah* days that
a woman could not demand a divorce?
That it was only the husband's decision to divorce?
The husband is the only one that can issue a divorce, but
if the woman presents sufficient claims to the בית דין *Beis Din*
and evidence, well, the question do you need evidence, then the בית
דין *Beis Din* will compel the man to give the divorce. Yeah,
yeah, sure, sure, המדיר את אשתו *HaMadir Et Ishto* is a lot
about that.
Yeah, I was going to say also, presumably it works the other
way around. It's like, I know the husband can divorce the woman
anyway, but even according to בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* says you need
to do it for cause if the husband says I find you
intolerable.
Yeah, yeah, well, there's always a lower threshold for the man. Okay,
anyway, moving on. So, claim number one, woman says טמאה temeiah, *teme'ah*,
she's believed and even she gets her כתובה ketubah, *kesubah*. Claim number
two, a woman says that we are, we can't continue living together,
either you can't give me kids or the even
more expansive claim of the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* where it's just, you know,
we're just estranged from one another, she's believed and she gets her
כתובה ketubah. *kesubah*. Number three, נטולה אני מן היהודים *Netulah ani min
ha'Yehudim*. That's why we're doing it. She took a vow to say
I will not, I cannot get sex from anybody, including you. Now,
what does that have to do with why they get a divorce?
I mean, she gets a divorce, she's not going to be able
to have sex with anybody either. It's not just the marriage to
this guy is preventing her. So, and anyway, why can't he just
annul it? Right? Or go to a חכם *chacham* to מתיר *matir*
it? So any guesses why this would mean that we would force
a divorce?
Could it be, I mean because it's sort of one of the
other things. I mean if she's willing to take a נדר *neder*
like that then
you have to say working
out so poorly that, you know,
but not just, correct, but not just so poorly,
actually the way it's assumed is if she's forbidden, if she's sincere
in forbidding herself with sex with everybody, it means that she's, she
can't tolerate sex. Okay, she probably has either some, you know, physiological
or other type of issue that makes sex so painful that she
cannot tolerate sex. So she has taken this vow. So we assume
that if a woman has gone to the stage of taking a
vow to this extreme, right, that, you know, that, that it must,
that we can't let her stay in this marriage if she possibly
can't, she can't.
What if he's okay with that?
Yeah, but that's again, well, she's not okay. Well, you mean she's
okay to be married to the guy if the guy isn't demanding
sex?
And clearly the guy is, clearly trying to get out of the
marriage.
Yeah, I mean if they've both worked it out, then exactly, then
nobody's coming to court. Okay, so right. And the other point is
that the גמרא *Gemara* just takes this for granted, that you're not,
nobody has, that you can't have a marriage without sex. Okay, but
you're right. If they've both worked it out, then this case isn't
being, then this case isn't being brought before anybody. Yeah.
Maybe she's what you'd call today a lesbian.
Yeah, maybe,
you know, so for whatever reason she can't tolerate, well, I don't
know because מן היהודים *min ha'Yehudim* does that include יהודיות *Yehudiyot* or
I don't know, anyway.
That she doesn't have a relationship that's not, she's saying she's forbidden
to all Jews.
Yeah, I know. So all right, let's not go there. Okay, fascinating
little digression. Charlie's going to give a שיעור *shiur* on that
tomorrow in shul. So anyway, now of course you realize that a
possible point here is like, like all of these since they're just
believing claims, you know, are claims that somebody could make even if
they're not true, right? And especially if they're given the כתובה ketubah.
as a result, okay? So what's, you know, so how are we
going to deal with this? Okay, and by the case of the
נדר, she can make the נדר, get divorced, and then go get
an התרה on the נדר, you know, go to some city where
they haven't heard about her and whatever. So anyway, so let's take
a look. So the גמרא says—so the משנה mishna says, חזרו לומר,
chazru lomar,
then they went back and they said, they revised their ruling, and
they said, שלא תהא אשה נותנת עיניה באחר ומקלקלת על בעלה. shelo
te'ei ishah notenes eineha be'acher umekalkeles al ba'alah. The woman should not
be, you know, sort of like looking at some other guy, meaning
interested in another man other than her husband, and she's ruining her
marriage with her husband as a result without sufficient cause. And therefore
now what do we say as a result? האומרת טמאה אני לך
תביא ראיה לדבריה. ha'omeret temeiah ani lach tavi rayah lidevareha. If
she—so then okay, then they stay married. If she says I'm טמאה,
then she has to prove it, and if not they stay married.
השמים ביני ובינך יעשה דרך בקשה. hashamayim beini uveinecha yaaseh derech bakashah.
So he should try to appease her. Okay, and the ירושלמי says
something, make a nice meal for her, סעודה, seudah, like what? You
can't give me kids. So if it's about a strange man, okay,
counsel then, go see a marriage counselor, try to work it out.
Right, if it's about not having kids, it's like, you know, it's
like what he said. Well, try to make her be, you know,
bring her flowers, do nice things, you know, maybe make her happy
even though she doesn't have kids. You know, it's sort of like,
you know, good luck, like what אלקנה Elkanah says to חנה, Channah,
הלא טוב אני לך מעשרה בנים, halo tov ani lach measarah banim,
which is no. So anyway,
so you know, anyway, so that's like the real—that might be why
the ירושלמי explained that it was about a strange man and nothing
else, because at least this some degree you can understand the response.
הנזורה אני מן היהודים—now hanezurah ani min hayehudim this is the harshest
one. If she takes a vow not to have sex from Jews,
יפר לחלקו, yafer lechelko, annul his—this we've quoted this before but we
didn't appreciate the context. He annuls his part because it's דברים שבינו
לבינה, ותהא משמשתו, vetehei meshameshto, and then they continue having sex, ותהא
נזורה מן היהודים, vetehei nezurah min hayehudim, if she ever gets divorced,
she'll be forbidden on other people. So which basically means like, we're
not believing her. If we're not believing her, then you know, then—we're
not
believing her that she says הנזורה אני מן היהודים. hanezurah ani min
hayehudim.
No, no, no. Without, right. Obviously the vow is binding. We're not
believing her concern about what stood behind the vow. And we're going
to tell her you still have to have sex with your husband,
I'm sorry, because that's the consequence. Same about the consequence about יורה
כחץ. We're not really believing her, you know? I mean, so it's
not just—it's like interesting, right? You could have said we believe her
but we're not going to act upon it anyway, right? But if
we're going to believe her but not force a divorce, but we're
still going to believe her to some degree, you would have assumed
more of an accommodation. It's really no, all or nothing. Either you
believe her or you don't believe her.
Okay, so from
divorce and כתובה, ketubah now we're saying no divorce at all. It's
what, right.
Yeah, you could have had a middle position. You could have said
we force a divorce but you don't get a כתובה. ketubah? Okay,
you know? And that could have been a very like, you know,
reasonable middle position. That's by the way what רמב"ם says when a
woman says, "I find this man intolerable, I can't continue to have
sex with him." רמב"ם says we force a divorce, she doesn't get
a כתובה. So the not getting a כתובה sort of makes it
financially disadvantageous
to say this. So and so therefore there's some cost to saying
this and that makes it more believable when somebody makes that claim.
Okay, so you know, right now in terms of issues around עגונה,
agunah, like I mean, you know, like that would be like—if we
פוסקן pasken like the רמב"ם, it'd be wonderful. Who cares about the
כתובה? Basically, you say you can't go on living with the man
and you're entitled to a divorce, right? So anyway, but that is—so
that is a very reasonable middle position which was not adopted here.
Okay, so that's the negative consequence of all of this is that
a woman basically is the עגונה agunah type of a situation. A
woman says I can't have sex, you know, I find sex in
general intolerable or I just find my husband intolerable or whatever reason
he can't give me kids, etc. We basically ignore it. Okay, and
if you hear stories about בתי דין, batei din, often in Israel
or חרדי charedi בתי דין batei din or whatever, that you know
a couple goes to them and the woman says my husband all
these types of things, not just סתם stam estrangement, he beats me,
he this, he that, or whatever and they say go back, try
to work it out, שלום בית, shalom bayit, you know, and that's
really like a deep-seated attitude and we can't deny that that comes
a lot from this משנה, mishna you know. I'm serious. The משנה
Mishna says here it is and they say, now the difference
is that this there's no evidence other than her claim, and it's
not that he beats me and it's not whatever, right? So but
nevertheless the type of
answer of like יעשה פשרה ביניהם, yaaseh pesharah beinehem, יעשה דרך בקשה,
yaaseh derech bakashah, right, or ותהא משמשתו, vetehei meshameshto, right? Now again,
it's partly because there's no evidence. evidence to it, right? If there
was evidence then presumably we wouldn't say any of that. If there
was evidence we'd say, "No, that is intolerable." So that's what gets
lost. What gets lost is, is that the משנה is saying that
those conditions are intolerable and they would have to get divorced. The
only shift is that, you know, we don't believe. But, but nevertheless
what happens is like this whole deep-set attitude. And the other problem
that happens is is this issue about שמא נתנה עיניה באחר. shema
natna eineha ba'acher. And that how much does a when a woman
finds a marriage intolerable, you know, for, you know, you know, for
whatever reason, estrangement or, you know, you know, even bigger reasons, is
the response like, "Oh, well that's undermining Jewish marriage," because any power
that we give the woman to sort of say that this is
intolerable and I need a divorce basically, if you give a woman
an out, right, then that's she's נתנה עיניה באחר. natna eineha ba'acher.
It's giving her any, right? Of course the point is a man
can be נתן עיניו באחרת natan einav be'acheret and just divorce his
wife. That doesn't endanger Jewish marriage, but for some, you know, פוסקים,
poskim, you know, this this endangers Jewish marriage. That a woman could
want to leave and and she would actually have a position of
power to push for, you know, to to get a divorce out
of the marriage. So there's a lot of like problematic things that
emerge and I'm not saying it's in the משנה itself, you know,
because as I said, the משנה really is is dealing with a
question about not about, you know, is a woman if a woman
has if this is this problem a big enough a big enough
problem to demand a divorce? Yes, right? Would we say that we're
not going to act on it if we knew it was really
a problem? No, no, no, of course we don't have a problem
that if the woman really proves it that we we're not concerned
of נתנה עיניה באחר. natna eineha ba'acher. And that of course we
would demand a divorce, right? The whole issue is about can we
believe her? But nevertheless what winds up becoming in the forefront is
is stick with the marriage, we can't give you the ability to
get out of the marriage, etc., etc. So it's a that's like
a real problematic part that emerges in terms of the history of
הלכה halacha and now I'm going to turn to like the very
positive part that emerges from the תמהני לך. temeihani lach. Did you
want to say something at this stage?
There's a fundamental assumption under all of this which is just where
for a woman who looks at another man with desire it's a
sin, and if a man does, he's fulfilling a need.
Right! Right, and then that reflects a, well, polygamous society in which
a woman can only have one man and a man can have
multiple wives. Right? So, okay, absolutely. Now, let's talk for a minute
about the first part, which is just as important, which is a
woman basically comes and says to her husband,
"I committed adultery." According to this, I'm sorry, you're not believed, we
don't have to get a divorce. Okay, if they want, if they
want to not get a divorce, if they want to work it
out, they don't have to get a divorce because she's not believed.
Or a woman says to her husband the כהן, kohen, "I was
raped." Okay, they don't have to get a divorce. Or a woman
says to her now, why not? That could be good. That's what
I'm saying. That's the good part about the first part of the
משנה that if they want to stay married we're not going to
say you can't live together because halachically we don't believe you. Because
of a חשש?
chashash? What do
you
as a result of the rape or whatever?
Yeah, as a true relationship but we don't believe you. And then,
you know, three months later she's pregnant.
Right, well how do you know who the father is? Five different
color, okay, right, right, right. So if there's evidence, and the hardest
cases about these come when the husband is like suspicious of his
wife and he hires a private investigator and then they have all
of this like evidence, right? I mean I know a case like
this and they got all this evidence and then they got divorced
or whatever and then they want to get back together again. I
was like, "You know, you idiot, you got all that evidence" or
whatever, right? And then the question is what level of evidence counts
as evidence? Okay, but here what we're saying is because of this
issue about about maybe she's just trying to force a divorce, we
don't believe her. The hardest prob— the harder problem is when she
tells him before marriage. This wouldn't be a problem with a ישראל
yisrael but it would be a problem with a כהן. kohen. So
if a woman basically says that she has a sexual history that
would make her אסורה asura to a כהן, kohen, which basically would
be not if she had premarital sex but if she slept with
a non-Jew, okay, then it would really be a problem because we
can't say שמא נתנה עיניה באחר. shema natna eineha ba'acher. We would
have to believe her. So women are are, you know,
advised—I mean depends on who they ask—but they're advised to basically say,
"You know, don't go into any details, like and if you need
to share the specifics you can wait until after your marriage." So
not to like hide some—no, not to like mislead—but you don't he
doesn't have to, you know, he can get a—you can he can
read between the lines, but you know, but don't give any specifics
until you're married and then officially he won't believe you, right? Yes.
There's a disconnect here between
following
the rules and what the court knows. What about the person themselves?
Right.
Thank you! Excellent! I did so good, I didn't have to ask
that question. So that's the next question, which is, which is, okay,
you're not going to officially believe me, but I know what I
did and how can I, right, continue to go on living with
my husband? I want to follow הלכה. Halacha. Okay, or here's another
problem that they ask. Whatever happened to שויה אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא? Shavya
Nafsha Chaticha DeIsura? Whatever happened to the fact that David actually does
believe her, you can tell me I don't have to, but in
practice I do, and shouldn't that make her אסור to me? Okay.
So, this is the problem the ראשונים Rishonim really grapple with. One
answer is, ready for it? אפקינו רבנן לקידושין מיניה. Afkinu Rabanan Lekiddushin
Minei. Okay, which basically just means like, yeah, you know, because of
the concern about נתנה באחר, Natnat BeAcher, we would just retroactively undo
the קידושין. Kiddushin. Now of course the problem is, is
that apply to the second part of the משנה or you're saying
just only the first?
No, the second part. Because that's how by not we don't believe
her. How can but if we don't believe her, let's say it's
really true, then how do this כהן Kohen still continue living with
his wife? How does this man still continue living with his wife?
So the answer is, well, in those cases when it really was
true, we will have a behind the scenes הפקעת קידושין Hafkat Kiddushin
and wait,
but then he can't continue living with her then?
Yes he can. Why can't he? Because she never committed adultery. Yeah,
their continue living together would be an implicit remarry or something or
a first marriage actually. So, the problem is, as the ראשונים Rishonim
say, is that then if it was an אשת כהן Eshet Kohen
and the man she slept with was would have made her forbidden
even had she not been married, or I should say she slept
with a non-Jew while she was married, הפקעת קידושין Hafkat Kiddushin isn't
going to solve the problem. Anyway, that's one answer, that's a pretty
radical answer. The other answer is fascinating, which is that, at least
halfway, which is it says the תורה Torah only says that a
כהן Kohen can't marry such a woman, it never says that a
woman that such woman can't marry a כהן. Kohen. So what, so
in the case of כהן Kohen this does not work for the
adultery case. But in the case of כהן, Kohen, she could say
I know that I slept with a non-Jew or I did this
or I did that or whatever or she was raped, but I'm
allowed to sleep with my husband. It's just that he's not allowed
to sleep with me, but I'm allowed to sleep with him. So
I'm being מכשיר Machshir him or something. Well, according to הלכה, Halacha,
he's
my Halachic status vis-a-vis him, you know, is that he's allowed to
sleep with me. It becomes very weird. The other question though that's
asked is, okay, so that really people seriously question that if that's
true by כהן. Kohen. And number two is it only works for
the כהן Kohen case. It doesn't work for the ישראל Yisrael case.
So it basically sort of seems like what's really going on here
and this is a really interesting issue is that הלכה Halacha defines
reality. And if we have defined that as a matter of law
we are not believing the fact thing, then it has no legal
meaning. And that seems to be, like unless you have one of
those other answers, but that seems to be what's inescapable. Now the
problem is that still doesn't answer the problem about שויה אנפשיה חתיכה
דאיסורא. Shavya Nafsha Chaticha DeIsura. Because שויה אנפשיה חתיכה דאיסורא Shavya Nafsha
Chaticha DeIsura means witnesses come and say this is a kosher piece
of meat, a hundred witnesses testify, as a matter of law it
is a kosher piece of meat and I say I don't care
what those witnesses are saying, I am telling you it is חזיר.
Chazer. So הלכה Halacha is I'm not allowed to eat it. שויה
אנפשיה Shavya Nafsha when I means that I'm bound by my own
claims regardless of what its legal status is to everyone else. So
here the problem is is that what about שויה? Shavya? Forget what
she knows in her mind and what he believes in her mind
or whatever, like if he actually says it and he actually believes
it and says that he believes it, why doesn't that create a
reality of שויה? Shavya? And somehow, you know, it's whatever the answer
is not spelled out as right. Somehow it seems like we are
so saying that this is not believable that we basically somehow say
your שויה Shavya is בטל Batul or something to that effect. You
know, the fact that you believed her or whatever it's all based
on error, you weren't entitled to believe her, you weren't whatever etcetera
etcetera. So anyway, that is really, really fascinating because actually serious הלכה
Halacha gets פסקן Paskin based on this. So the reversal is very
helpful in the case of טמאה אני לך, Tamei Ani Lach, not
so helpful in the case of a marriage that isn't working out.
It's helpful in cases of a marriage that is working out that
they don't have to act on the divorce, not so... yeah.
So
unless I'm missing something like very basic here. Yep. There doesn't seem
to be any consideration or room for the psychic necessity and emotional
necessity of acknowledging the rape on the part of the woman and
having her work through that reality. Right. Yes. For us this so
that she can re-acclimate herself to a healthy relationship.
You're completely correct. Meaning even within the sympathetic פוסקים Poskim that are
going to say, "Well we don't believe you" and so on, and
you tell the husband you're not allowed to believe her, okay, how
are they supposed where's the pastoral element, how are they supposed to
like work that through, you know? So you work it... some way
with a pro forma, you know, air quotes or I don't know,
but you have to manage to walk that balance. Like, yeah, you
allow them to work it through and somehow officially you say, you
know, but it’s it’s hard. I want to just end by reading
a really important line in תוספות *Tosafot*. Take a look at the
large, the largest
of the lines towards the end where he says ומיהו נראה *u-mihu
nireh*. He says, it appears דאף למשנה אחרונה אם אומרת אשה טמאה
אני לך *d'af l’mishna achrona im omeret isha tmeia ani lach*. Where
are we looking? The last, the first of the widest lines of
תוספות *Tosafot*. You have it? Towards the end, like the last ten
words. ומיהו נראה *u-mihu nireh*, he says, דאף למשנה אחרונה אם אומרת
אשה טמאה אני לך *d'af l’mishna achrona im omeret isha tmeia ani
lach*, ואמר הבעל שמאמינה *v'amar haba'al shema'amina*, because that was never explicit
in the משנה *Mishnah*. So let’s say the husband says, does the
שוויא אנפשיה *shavya nafshia* become a problem? דאסורה לו *de'asura lo*. So
his first move is actually, yeah, if he says he believes her,
then you’ve got, then it’s שוויא *shavya*. And that’s why we tell
people like I said before, maybe we would override a שוויא *shavya*,
but it actually, most פוסקים *poskim* assume no, you better not say
you believe her, then it becomes a שוויא *shavya*. So תוספות *Tosafot*
says, okay, if he believes her, it becomes a שוויא *shavya*, דאסורה
לו *de'asura lo*, ואפילו תחזור בה האשה ותאמר באונס היה *v'afillu tachzor
ba ha'isha v'tomar b'onus haya*. So this is a case about, not
a כהן *Kohen*, about a case of adultery. So now he said,
oh my god, you believed her, so now it’s going to, now
you’re going to have to get a divorce. And then the woman
says, actually, she changes her story, actually wait wait wait, it wasn’t
adultery, I was raped. And then he says, okay, I believe that.
Alright, so תוספות *Tosafot* says, okay, so you might think that since
his first שוויא *shavya* was based on her first claim, if she
reverses her first claim, maybe he’s able to reverse his שוויא *shavya*.
Okay? But he says no, he can't change it, once he’s stuck
by שוויא *shavya*. So here it’s very מחמיר *machmir*, but then he
says, ויש אומרים דמשמתינן ליה על שגרם שתאסר אשתו עליו *v'yesh omrim
d'mshamtinan leh al shegaram shetei'aser ishto alav*, that if somebody chooses to
believe his wife, we put him in חרם *cherem*, because now you’re
forcing a divorce, ועובר על חרם דרבינו גרשום *v'over al cherem d'Rabbeinu
Gershom*. How are you forcing a divorce? Because your wife wants to
stay married, she wants to work it through, and you by you
saying that you’re believing her, you’re forcing her to get divorced against
her will. Okay, so because according to הלכה *halakha*, she says she
committed adultery, according to הלכה *halakha* we don’t believe her, she’s entitled
to stay married, and you’re choosing to do a שוויא *shavya* and
impose on her a divorce against her will, so we're going to
put you in חרם *cherem*. So hopefully the result of putting you
in חרם *cherem* is, this is my point, that nobody is going
to believe their wife. And we say to the person, look, you
said you believed her, but did you realize that if you believe
her you're going to be in חרם *cherem*? So did you really
believe her? You know, so basically this is fascinating because it shows
how, you know, they try to create like a communal policy that
would navigate these types of issues. And this is still with us,
you know, sort of that as long as you don't
officially believe her, you don't have to deal with שוויא *shavya* and
then it doesn't have to be believed and they can stay married.
Even if you deep down
believe her. How does that work?